CURRICULUM VITAE

SIMON GATHATA WAINAINA P. O BOX 22061 - 00100, NAIROBI MOBILE: 0720 362 705

EMAIL: sg.wainaina@ yahoo.com

PERSONAL PROFILE

A result oriented professional accountant with diverse experience gained in dynamic and challenging environments. I am hardworking and honest with initiative and drive and possess good interpersonal, analytical and communication skills. I demonstrate integrity in my conduct and professionalism in my work.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

- 2014 Masters of Business Administration (Finance), University of Nairobi
- 2010 Bachelor of Commerce (Accounting) Second Class, Upper Division, KCA University
- 2005 **Diploma in Business Management** Kenya Institute of Management
- 1997 KCSE Certificate, Githiga High School
- 1993 KCPE Certificate, Giathieko Primary School

PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

2004 Certified Public Accountant - CPA (K), KCA University

OTHER QUALIFICATIONS

- 2015 Senior Management Course, Kenya School of Government
- 2015 Corporate Governance, Kenya School of Government
- 2012 Public Sector Financial Management

COMPUTER KNOWLEDGE

Microsoft Dynamics Navision, QuickBooks, Sage Pastel, PeachTree, Aren Payroll MS - Office: Excel, Word, Access and Outlook

PROFESSIONAL ASSOCIATION

Member - Institute of Certified Public Accountants (ICPAK) in Good Standing Status

EXPERIENCE SUMMARY

I have been gained extensive knowledge and diverse skills in Administration, Accounting, taxation, financial management, financial information analysis, project cost controlling and monitoring, project funds management, preparation of management accounts and financial reports, budgets, cash flow, maintenance and implementation of computerized financial accounting software's, setting up systems of internal controls, among other pertinent duties and offered a lead-hand in improving on efficiency and effectiveness.

I have had further training and experience in software development and deployment, Business Processes Re-engineering where extensive experience and knowledge has been gained towards customized business software solutions.

DETAILED WORK EXPERIENCE

1. Period: July 2012 – to Date

Position: Finance and Administration Officer

Company: Kenya Veterinary Board Industry: Regulatory Authority

DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

• In charge of day to day financial and administrative activities of the Board.

- Coordinating the preparation of the budgets and work plans.
- Developing prudent expenditure control procedures by monitoring utilization of capital and operational expenditure
- Coordinate preparation of timely and accurate financial reports, management accounts, cash flow projections, variance analysis adherence reporting requirements and deadlines
- Designing policies that enhance compliance to procedures of recording transactions
- Developing, implementing and maintaining financial policies, plans, procedures and adequate systems of internal control
- Approving and oversee posting of transaction in Microsoft Dynamics ERP Software.
- Coordinate procurement activities ensuring adherence to procurement laws and regulations
- Assets Management including updating assets catalogue, insuring, repairs and maintenance and safeguarded against misuse.
- Coordinating and monitoring implementation of work plan and strategic plan
- Coordinating Internal and External Audit and responding to queries
- Ensure compliance with statutory regulations and reporting, payment of taxes, and adherence to statutory regulations
- Payment of statutory obligation, NHIF, NSSF, PAYE and staff deductions
- Preparation of financial statements in accordance to IPSAS, IAS and GAAP
- Project accounting and analysis, monitoring expenditure and reporting on projects and activities performed.
- Supervision of staff, allocation of duties and responsibilities

ACHIEVEMENT

- Team Leader in Business Processes Re-engineering and development of automation workflows
- Team leader in design and development of Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) Software modules
- Successfully managed system change over from manual to automation
- Developed a financial report writer tool automating preparation of financial statements
- Development of procedures and operations manual
- Spearheading the ISO process, moving from 0% to 60%

2. Period: April 2008 – to June 2012

Position: Senior Accountant Company: CB Richard Ellis Ltd Industry: Real Estate and Valuation

DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

- Supervise posting of transactions in Sage Pastel Computerised accounting system
- Coordinating preparation of timely and accurate financial reports, management accounts, cash flow projections, various ad hoc reports adhering to reporting deadlines
- Preparation of budgets and budgetary Control ensuring spending is within budget, through

- periodic variance analysis.
- Supervising and providing support to the accounts assistance and cashier and ensure accounting duties are done on time including training and offering guidance to the team in the finance department
- Ensure that transactions relating to VAT, Income Tax and Witholding taxes are accurately determined, properly recorded and paid timely as per the law and regulations
- Coordinate payment to suppliers and other obligations as they arise
- Ensure strong, sound and practical systems of internal controls are in place to safeguard company assets against fraud and theft, overseeing implementation of such controls to financial processes and transactions.
- Ensure that all funds are receipted and banked.
- Coordinating preparation of bank reconciliation statements
- Coordinating of external audit, preparation of audit lead schedules and addressing audit queries.
- Designing policies and procedures enhancing compliance to recording and posting transactions.
- Payroll administration and payment of staff Statutory deductions like N.H.I.F and N.S.S.F
- Other administrative responsibilities as they arise

ACHIEVEMENT

- Successfully implemented Sage Pastel Accounting System automating finance operations
- Implemented Aren Payroll system automation payroll functions
- Developed property rental database using MS Access

3. Period: April 2007 – March 2008

Position: Group Accountant
Company: Norwich Union Group
Industry: Real Estate and Investment

DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

- Ensuring complete and accurate accounting, recording and posting of inter-company transactions for all companies in the group and segmental reporting
- Preparation of consolidated management accounts and reports with precise accuracy and completeness using IAS, IFRS.i.e. cash flow statements, income statements, Balance sheet
- Preparation of budgeting and budgetary control
- Designing systems of internal controls to enhance compliance to laid down procedures.
- Timely billings to customers
- Taxation responsibilities for the group and the affiliated companies ensuring compliance to statutory regulation for P.A.Y.E, VAT, With-holding tax, Instalment Tax,
- Payroll administration and payment of staff Statutory deductions like N.H.I.F and N.S.S.F
- Accounting for dividends and interests on loans to members.
- Maintenance of Fixed Asset register
- Ensure accurate and timely payment to suppliers and other obligations as they fall due.
- Coordinating external audit and preparing audit lead schedules
- Other administrative responsibilities as they arise.

ACHIEVEMENT

- Developed a segmental reporting structure using crystal report writer tool
- Implemented Aren Payroll system automation payroll functions

4. Period: January 2007 to March 2007 Position: Internal Audit Assistant

Company: Morisson Engineering Limited Industry: Engineering and Construction

DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

Audit of bank activities, debtors, creditors, stock and payroll transactions.

Examining correctness of bank reconciliation, debtors, creditors, stock accounts and payroll.

Advising management on strengthening internal control weaknesses

Verification of vouchers ensure compliance with laid down procedures and guidelines

5. Period: January 2003 – December 2006

Position: Accountant

Company: Maina Njanga Advocates

Industry: Law Firm

DUTIES AND RESPONSIBILITIES

- Preparations of financial reports and management accounts
- Posting of transactions in QuickBooks Accounting System using
- Prepared of bank reconciliation statements monthly for all bank accounts
- Payroll administration and staff statutory deductions i.e. N.H.I.F and N.S.S.F
- Taxation compliance in P.A.Y.E, VAT, With-holding and Instalment Taxes
- Coordinated external audit including preparation of audit schedules.
- Budgeting and Budgetary Control including Cash flow forecast, variance analysis etc.
- Receipting of organisation funds and banking
- Coordinating payments to clients and suppliers.
- Administrative duties including renewal of practicing licenses, renewal of insurance policies

ACHIEVEMENT

- Successfully implemented QuickBooks Accounting System automating operations
- Starting up the accounting department

REFEREES

David Wachira Gachoki Antony Maina Mwangi Godfrey Ngugi Bedan Finance Officer P. O Box 45870 - 00100 P. O Box 14815 - 00100

FAO Somalia Nairobi Nairobi

P. O Box 30470 - 00100 Phone 0722577481/07861270 Phone 072215026

Nairobi Email: E-mail:

Phone 0720 285796 mwangi_antony@yahoo.com godfreybedan@yahoo.com

E-mail: wagach@gmail.com